<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><article number="Article XIII"><catchline>Revenue and Taxation</catchline><section number="Article XIII, Section 1"><histories></histories><catchline>[Fiscal year.]</catchline><tab/>The Legislature shall by statute establish the fiscal year of the State.</section><section number="Article XIII, Section 2"><histories></histories><catchline>[Property tax.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(1)">
So that each person and corporation pays a tax in proportion to the fair market value of his, her, or its tangible property, all tangible property in the State that is not exempt under the laws of the United States or under this Constitution shall be:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(1)(a)">
assessed at a uniform and equal rate in proportion to its fair market value, to be ascertained as provided by law; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(1)(b)">
taxed at a uniform and equal rate.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(2)">
Each corporation and person in the State or doing business in the State is subject to taxation on the tangible property owned or used by the corporation or person within the boundaries of the State or local authority levying the tax.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(3)">
The Legislature may provide by statute that land used for agricultural purposes be assessed based on its value for agricultural use.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(4)">
The Legislature may by statute determine the manner and extent of taxing livestock.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(5)">
The Legislature may by statute determine the manner and extent of taxing or exempting intangible property, except that any property tax on intangible property may not exceed .005 of its fair market value.  If any intangible property is taxed under the property tax, the income from that property may not also be taxed.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 2(6)">
Tangible personal property required by law to be registered with the State before it is used on a public highway or waterway, on public land, or in the air may be exempted from property tax by statute.  If the Legislature exempts tangible personal property from property tax under this Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 2(6)" start="0">(6)</xref>, it shall provide for the payment of uniform statewide fees or uniform statewide rates of assessment or taxation on that property in lieu of the property tax.  The fair market value of any property exempted under this Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 2(6)" start="0">(6)</xref> shall be considered part of the State tax base for determining the debt limitation under <xref depth="2" refnumber="Article XIV" start="0">Article XIV</xref>.</subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 3"><histories></histories><catchline>[Property tax exemptions.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)">
The following are exempt from property tax:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(a)">
property owned by the State;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(b)">
property owned by a public library;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(c)">
property owned by a school district;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(d)">
property owned by a political subdivision of the State, other than a school district, and located within the political subdivision;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(e)">
property owned by a political subdivision of the State, other than a school district, and located outside the political subdivision unless the Legislature by statute authorizes the property tax on that property;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(f)">
property owned by a nonprofit entity used exclusively for religious, charitable, or educational purposes;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(g)">
places of burial not held or used for private or corporate benefit;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(h)">
farm equipment and farm machinery as defined by statute;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(i)">
water rights, reservoirs, pumping plants, ditches, canals, pipes, flumes, power plants, and transmission lines to the extent owned and used by an individual or corporation to irrigate land that is:<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(i)(i)">
within the State; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(i)(ii)">
owned by the individual or corporation, or by an individual member of the corporation; and</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)"><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(i)">
if owned by a nonprofit entity and used within the State to irrigate land, provide domestic water, as defined by statute, or provide water to a public water supplier:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(i)(A)">
water rights; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(i)(B)">
reservoirs, pumping plants, ditches, canals, pipes, flumes, and, as defined by statute, other water infrastructure;</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(ii)">
land occupied by a reservoir, ditch, canal, or pipe that is exempt under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(i)(B)" start="0">(1)(j)(i)(B)</xref> if the land is owned by the nonprofit entity that owns the reservoir, ditch, canal, or pipe; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(iii)">
land immediately adjacent to a reservoir, ditch, canal, or pipe that is exempt under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(i)(B)" start="0">(1)(j)(i)(B)</xref> if the land is:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(iii)(A)">
owned by the nonprofit entity that owns the adjacent reservoir, ditch, canal, or pipe; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(1)(j)(iii)(B)">
reasonably necessary for the maintenance or for otherwise supporting the operation of the reservoir, ditch, canal, or pipe.</subsection></subsection></subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)"><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)">
The Legislature may by statute exempt the following from property tax:<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(i)">
tangible personal property constituting inventory present in the State on January 1 and held for sale in the ordinary course of business;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(ii)">
tangible personal property present in the State on January 1 and held for sale or processing and shipped to a final destination outside the State within 12 months;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(iii)">
subject to Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(b)" start="0">(2)(b)</xref>, property to the extent used to generate and deliver electrical power for pumping water to irrigate lands in the State;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(iv)">
up to 45% of the fair market value of residential property, as defined by statute;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(v)">
household furnishings, furniture, and equipment used exclusively by the owner of that property in maintaining the owner's home; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(vi)">
tangible personal property that, if subject to property tax, would generate an inconsequential amount of revenue.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(b)">
The exemption under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 3(2)(a)(iii)" start="0">(2)(a)(iii)</xref> shall accrue to the benefit of the users of pumped water as provided by statute.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)">
The following may be exempted from property tax as provided by statute:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(a)">
property owned by a disabled person who, during military training or a military conflict, was disabled in the line of duty in the military service of the United States or the State; </subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(b)">
property owned by the unmarried surviving spouse or the minor orphan of a person who:<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(b)(i)">
is described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(a)" start="0">(3)(a)</xref>; or</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(b)(ii)">
during military training or a military conflict, was killed in action or died in the line of duty in the military service of the United States or the State; and</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(3)(c)">
real property owned by a person in the military or the person's spouse, or both, and used as the person's primary residence, if the person serves under an order to federal active duty out of state for at least 200 days in a calendar year or 200 consecutive days.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 3(4)">
The Legislature may by statute provide for the remission or abatement of the taxes of the poor.</subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 4"><histories></histories><catchline>[Other taxes.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 4(1)">
Nothing in this Constitution may be construed to prevent the Legislature from providing by statute for taxes other than the property tax and for deductions, exemptions, and offsets from those other taxes.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 4(2)">
In a statute imposing an income tax, the Legislature may:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 4(2)(a)">
define the amount on which the tax is imposed by reference to a provision of the laws of the United States as from time to time amended; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 4(2)(b)">
modify or provide exemptions to a provision referred to in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 4(2)(a)" start="0">(2)(a)</xref>.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 5"><histories></histories><catchline>[Use and amount of taxes and expenditures.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(1)">
The Legislature shall provide by statute for an annual tax sufficient, with other revenues, to defray the estimated ordinary expenses of the State for each fiscal year.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(2)"><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(2)(a)">
For any fiscal year, the Legislature may not make an appropriation or authorize an expenditure if the State's expenditure exceeds the total tax provided for by statute and applicable to the particular appropriation or expenditure.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(2)(b)">
Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(2)(a)" start="0">(2)(a)</xref> does not apply to an appropriation or expenditure to suppress insurrection, defend the State, or assist in defending the United States in time of war.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(3)">
For any debt of the State, the Legislature shall provide by statute for an annual tax sufficient to pay:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(3)(a)">
the annual interest; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(3)(b)">
the principal within 20 years after the final passage of the statute creating the debt.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(4)">
Except as provided in <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article X, Section 5(5)(a)" start="0">Article X, Section 5, Subsection (5)(a)</xref>, the Legislature may not impose a tax for the purpose of a political subdivision of the State, but may by statute authorize political subdivisions of the State to assess and collect taxes for their own purposes.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(5)">
All revenue from taxes on intangible property or from a tax on income shall be used to support the systems of public education and higher education as defined in <xref depth="3" refnumber="Article X, Section 2" start="0">Article X, Section 2</xref>.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)">
Proceeds from fees, taxes, and other charges related to the operation of motor vehicles on public highways and proceeds from an excise tax on liquid motor fuel used to propel those motor vehicles shall be used for:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(a)">
statutory refunds and adjustments and costs of collection and administration;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(b)">
the construction, maintenance, and repair of State and local roads, including payment for property taken for or damaged by rights-of-way and for associated administrative costs;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(c)">
driver education;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(d)">
enforcement of state motor vehicle and traffic laws; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(e)">
the payment of the principal of and interest on any obligation of the State or a city or county, issued for any of the purposes set forth in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(6)(b)" start="0">(6)(b)</xref> and to which any of the fees, taxes, or other charges described in this Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(6)" start="0">(6)</xref> have been pledged, including any paid to the State or a city or county, as provided by statute.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(7)">
Fees and taxes on tangible personal property imposed under Section 2, Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(6)" start="0">(6)</xref> of this article are not subject to Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(6)" start="0">(6)</xref> of this Section 5 and shall be distributed to the taxing districts in which the property is located in the same proportion as that in which the revenue collected from real property tax is distributed.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(8)">
A political subdivision of the State may share its tax and other revenues with another political subdivision of the State as provided by statute.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(9)">
Beginning July 1, 2016, the aggregate annual revenue from all severance taxes, as those taxes are defined by statute, except revenue that by statute is used for purposes related to any federally recognized Indian tribe, shall be deposited annually into the permanent State trust fund under <xref depth="3" refnumber="Article XXII, Section 4" start="0">Article XXII, Section 4</xref>, as follows:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(9)(a)">
25% of the first $50,000,000 of aggregate annual revenue;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(9)(b)">
50% of the next $50,000,000 of aggregate annual revenue; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 5(9)(c)">
75% of the aggregate annual revenue that exceeds $100,000,000.</subsection></subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 6"><histories></histories><catchline>[State Tax Commission.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(1)">
There shall be a State Tax Commission consisting of four members, not more than two of whom may belong to the same political party.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(2)">
With the consent of the Senate, the Governor shall appoint the members of the State Tax Commission for such terms as may be provided by statute.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)">
The State Tax Commission shall:
<subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)(a)">
administer and supervise the State's tax laws;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)(b)">
assess mines and public utilities and have such other powers of original assessment as the Legislature may provide by statute;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)(c)">
adjust and equalize the valuation and assessment of property among the counties;</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)(d)">
as the Legislature provides by statute, review proposed bond issues, revise local tax levies, and equalize the assessment and valuation of property within the counties; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(3)(e)">
have other powers as may be provided by statute.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 6(4)">
Notwithstanding the powers granted to the State Tax Commission in this Constitution, the Legislature may by statute authorize any court established under Article VIII to adjudicate, review, reconsider, or redetermine any matter decided by the State Tax Commission relating to revenue and taxation.</subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 7"><histories></histories><catchline>[County boards of equalization.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 7(1)">
In each county, there shall be a county board of equalization consisting of elected county officials as provided by statute.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 7(2)">
Each county board of equalization shall adjust and equalize the valuation and assessment of the real and personal property within its county, subject to the State Tax Commission's regulation and control as provided by law.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 7(3)">
The county boards of equalization shall have other powers as may be provided by statute.</subsection><subsection number="Article XIII, Section 7(4)">
Notwithstanding the powers granted to the State Tax Commission in this Constitution, the Legislature may by statute authorize any court established under Article VIII to adjudicate, review, reconsider, or redetermine any matter decided by a county board of equalization relating to revenue and taxation.</subsection></section><section number="Article XIII, Section 8"><histories></histories><catchline>[Annual statement.]</catchline><tab/>The State shall publish annually an accurate statement of the receipt and expenditure of public money in a manner provided by statute.</section></article>
