<article number="Article XXII"><catchline>Miscellaneous</catchline><section number="Article XXII, Section 1"><histories></histories><catchline>[Homestead exemption.]</catchline><tab/>The Legislature shall provide by statute for an exemption of a homestead, which may consist of one or more parcels of lands, together with the appurtenances and improvements thereon, from sale on execution.</section><section number="Article XXII, Section 3"><histories></histories><catchline>[Seat of government.]</catchline><tab/>The seat of state government shall be at Salt Lake City.</section><section number="Article XXII, Section 4"><histories></histories><catchline>[State trust fund -- Principal to be held in perpetuity -- Use of income.]</catchline><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(1)">
There is established a permanent state trust fund consisting of:
<subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(1)(a)">
as provided by statute or appropriation, funds that the state receives relating to the November 1998 settlement agreement with leading tobacco manufacturers;</subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(1)(b)">
money or other assets given to the fund under any provision of law;</subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(1)(c)">
severance tax revenue, as provided in <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XIII, Section 5(9)" start="0">Article XIII, Section 5, Subsection (9)</xref>; and</subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(1)(d)">
other funds and assets that the trust fund receives by bequest or private donation.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(2)">
Except as provided in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="Article XXII, Section 4(4)" start="0">(4)</xref>, the state treasurer shall, as provided by statute, hold all trust funds and assets in trust and invest them for the benefit of the people of the state in perpetuity.</subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(3)">
The income from the state trust fund shall be deposited into the General Fund.</subsection><subsection number="Article XXII, Section 4(4)">
With the concurrence of the governor and three-fourths of each house of the Legislature, funds or assets in the trust fund may be removed from the fund for deposit into the General Fund.</subsection></section><section number="Article XXII, Section 5"><histories></histories><catchline>[Officers may not profit.]</catchline><tab/>Each public officer who makes a profit from public money or uses public money for a purpose not authorized by law shall be guilty of a felony and shall be punished as provided by law, but part of the punishment shall be disqualification to hold public office.</section></article>
